Finding Aid for the Vanderbilt Garden Club Records
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Vanderbilt Garden Club Records
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0473
2.52 linear feet
Historical Note
A brief history of the Vanderbilt Garden Club for Campus Beautification comes from a welcome and introduction by then president Ida Long Rogers on the occasion of a meeting hosted by Mrs. Constance Gee at the Chancellor’s residence Braeburn on May 6, 2002:
Back in 1927 Mary Henderson Kirkland, wife of the then Chancellor called together a small group of faculty wives and wives of members of the Board of Trust and asked their help with the beautification of the campus. What developed was a loosely knit group who literally did do the ground work. It was not until 1935 that a formal charter was drawn up and the Vanderbilt Garden Club became a reality. The charter limited the membership to 25, by invitation only, with annual dues set at $1.00.
Times have changed and over the years there was discussion of the importance of not losing sight of the history of those early days.
A history became a reality in The Real Dirt: A History of the Vanderbilt Garden Club for Campus Beautification, compiled and edited by Sharon Hogge and members of the Vanderbilt Garden Club and published in 1998.
The VGC has traditionally communicated with the Chancellors about the ongoing work of the club, and the Chancellors in turn have supported in different ways the club’s work.
The Vanderbilt Garden Club has taken on a number of important projects to beautify the campus over the years. The Iris Project of the late 1990’s was one of them, identifying, purchasing, and planting old varieties of irises
.
The Iris Project was of especial interest because of the number of people associated with Vanderbilt and Peabody who achieved important recognition and distinction for their growing and hybridization of irises. This list includes Clarence Connell (Dauntless, 1929); T. Alibone Washington and Mary Geddes Stahlman (Mary Geddes, 1931); Chancellor James Kirkland (Copper Lustre and Junaluska, 1934); Jesse Wills, (Chivalry, 1944; Natchez Trace, 1964; Starshine, Rose Garland, Russet Wings, Glacier Gold). Roy Appleton, L.C. Glenn, Ruth Hall, Bruce Payne, Mrs. James Reed, and Hilda Willems, also iris growers of note, made important contributions to the plantings for the Vanderbilt and Peabody campuses.
Many of the magnolia trees that encircle the campus were grown from seed propagated and planted under the direction of Jack Lynn who worked for 27 years for the Building and Grounds Department. It was Margaret Branscomb (1896-1992 ), a long time VGC member and wife of Chancellor Harvie Branscomb, who put forward this idea of the circle of magnolias during her time as President of the VGC in 1954. Other trees were grown in nurseries and were gifts from individuals. These magnolias, which were planted in the late 1950’s, have reached maturity and stand as one of the most significant accomplishments of the Vanderbilt Garden Club and certainly as Margaret Branscomb’s and Jack Lynn’s enduring gift to Vanderbilt University.
The records of this organization reflect the planning and work of the club’s members over the nearly eight decades of the existence of the Vanderbilt Garden Club. Founded in 1927, the VGC was an active organization for the beautification of the Vanderbilt Campus until the fall of 2006, when the decision was made to disband, as the work of the club is now being done by professional landscaping crews.
Scope and Content Note
This collection of 2.5 linear feet comprising six boxes contains all materials and records that have been generated and kept by the Vanderbilt Garden Club and includes history essays, minutes, photographs, audio tapes of meetings, programs, a scrapbook, and other items.
- Correspondence
  - History of the VGC, 1931-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1969-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - April 5, 1982; April 7, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ava Sellers to Judson Newbern re: McTyeire Hall, July 2, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Records of the Presidents
  - Ava Sellers, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ann Tarbel1, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mary Cannon, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jean Wright, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Robbie Shackleford remembers - Records, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elva Darby - 1984-1986 (includes landscaping of the Hobbs Sculpture area) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Holladay, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ida Long Rogers, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mary Roberts - 1990-1992; Dorothy Jean Wright, Vice-President; Fran Glidewell, recording secretary (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Frances Hardie, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Marie Wasson, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sharon Hogge - Spring 1996 - Spring, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fran Glidewell, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ida Long Rogers, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kay Hall, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jean Wright, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Constitution and By-Laws
  - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws of the VGC, adopted Spring, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, adopted 1946, amended, 1968, 1987, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, adopted 1946; amended, 1948, 1949, 1953, 1957, 1964, 1968, 1987, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Constitution and By-Laws Revisions, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Histories of the VGC
  - History, minutes, other notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1965 History of the the VGC by Aileen Bishop (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Historical notes about the VGC (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Notices of Meetings
  - November 9, 1970 - April, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - April 14, 1980 - October 28, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1992 - Fall 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1996-1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Spring 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Minutes of Meetings
  - 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ideas for Meetings (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Other Records
  - Margaret Branscomb - Recollections by members of the VGC; Tennessean article by Louise Davis, Oct. 4, 1987; Letter from Margaret Branscomb, May 13, 1987; Margaret Branscomb’s statement of appreciation of Mr. Jack Lynn, April 14, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Margaret V. Branscomb and Chancellor Harvie Branscomb (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Margaret V. Branscomb and Chancellor Harvie Branscomb (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. George Mayfield’s notes for a meeting (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, correspondence, and other - 1990’s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Officers VGC, 1998-2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Membership and Dues Lists
  - February 1, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1957-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dues and membership notebooks, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1974-1996 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - updates and changes, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - March 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Financial Records
  - Statements, cancelled checks, deposit slips (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Accounts, bills, notes, and receipts (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Bank records - 1998; 1999, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Accounts Ledger - 1995 – 2001 - membership dues; contributions (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Landscaping expenses, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Records of Pam Sevy, VU Landscape Architect, Dept. of Campus Planning, 1990-1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Records of Pam Sevy, VU Landscape Architect, Dept. of Campus Planning, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Iris Project
  - Records of the Iris Project - 1986-1988 including membership list Spring, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (1), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (2), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (3), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (4), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (5) Roots – Journal of the Historic Iris Preservation Society; Spring 1996; Fall 1996, 1996-1997; Spring 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (6) Historic Iris Preservation Society, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (7) “Nashville’s Iris Season” by Jesse E. Wills, 1996-1997; July 3, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (8), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (9), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Bicentennial Iris Project by Sharon Hogge (10), 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Iris Project, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Invitation for the Bicentennial Dedication of Historic Iris, April 21, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Articles and other writings on Chancellor James Kirkland and growing Irises (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Clarence P. Connell - VU Engineering Class of 1906 - biographical information and correspondence (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Clarence P. Connell - VU Engineering Class of 1906 - biographical information and other; Volunteer Gardener, Spring 1945; “Treasure Chest” in the Tennessean, May 18, 1958; garden photograph (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Iris at Peabody College – articles - Roy Appleton, 1894-1965 (1) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Iris at Peabody College - articles and speeches (2) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Iris Time in Tennessee” by Millie Wilder in The Tennessee Conservationist, March/April 1986 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Articles on Sam Caldwell, Iris grower (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Vanderbilt Garden Club Projects, 1950-1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Projects - 1951-1979; 1950-1954; History of projects 1989-1995; other projects and photographs (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Planting plan for the Vanderbilt Campus by Ronald J. Sias, Landscape Architect (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Lists of plantings and projects since 1970 and other historical information (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Notes on the boxwoods at Sarratt Center, 1974-1980 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - List of trees( dated 1954) on the Vanderbilt University Campus (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Trees of Vanderbilt (Arboretum) and history of VGC projects 1989-1995; other items concerning VU trees (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Catalogue of the Species and Varieties of plants in the Vanderbilt Arboretum (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Artwork designs for VGC programs and article “Creating your own new Iris” (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Publications
  - The Real Dirt: A History of the Vanderbilt Garden Club for Campus Beautification, compiled and edited by Sharon Hogge and Members of the Vanderbilt Garden Club, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Real Dirt - proof copy, 1998, acknowledgements, Chapter 5 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Real Dirt - proof copy, 1998, chapters 6 – 8 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Real Dirt - proof copy, 1998, Appendices (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Real Dirt - papers from the time of its publication in, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Real Dirt - Information pertaining to its publication (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - VGC Invitation - poem by Virginia Holladay (1997?) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - “Rare Gardens at Vanderbilt” in Vanderbilt Alumnus, v. 7 n.7, p. 150, (May 1922) (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - “Magnolia Shelter” article from The Tennessean, Jan. 7, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - “Historical Paragraphs” George Peabody College for Teachers, 13 pages (2 copies), October 1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - “In Memoriam” Mrs. Hugh Morgan (Bobby) - remarks by Elva Darby, April 13, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - “Oaks and Magnolias, Ginkoes and Silver Bells” by Naomi Klein in Vanderbilt Alumnus, vol. 67, No. 4, Summer, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Articles from the Vanderbilt Register, Sept. 11, 1980; June 15, 1982; June 26, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - “Magnolia News” newsletter of Vanderbilt Woman’s Club, September 2002 - April 2004 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - “Here We Grow Again: In Quarter Century, University Almost Triples in Size” - April 2005 (Campus Planning and Construction ) (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Other
  - Bronze Plaque - “Under the parent of this tree at Cambridge, Massachusetts, George Washington first took command of the American Army, July 3, 1775. Planted by the Vanderbilt Garden Club in Commemoration of the 200th Anniversary of his birth.” 12” x 4 ½” (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - “Washington Elm Plaque” - Information - Memo from Robert A. McGaw to Chancellor Alexander Heard (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum on symbols used to represent Vanderbilt University’s Mace, November 16, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “Mims” from the 1973 Centennial Commodore (VU Yearbook) and “Rotier” (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gardening with Books (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Peabody Tour Information (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Audio Tapes
  - Audio tapes (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ava Sellers, Mrs. Branscomb, Japanese “Gardens,” 1975. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Tribute to Mrs. Branscomb by Blanche Henry Weaver and Faye Wyatt (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Audio tapes (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - VGC - Jane Auerbach, 90 years old, reminisces, undated. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Jean Wright’s meeting, some reminiscences, Nov. 10, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Audio tapes (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Mary Wade, 1996. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - VGC for Campus Beautification, April 21, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook
  - Scrapbook - includes photographs and articles about the VGC (Box 6, Folder 4)